from scadden the standard formula is a
solvy 2 podcast for UK and European
Insurance professionals join us as
scadden partner Robert chaplain leads
conversations with industry
practitioners and explores solvy 2
developments that matter to
you welcome back to the standard formula
podcast today we'll be discussing
presedential Insurance regulation in
Japan which is a Hot Topic on our Radars
and forms an important backdrop to the
reinsurance boom we've been seeing in
Japan this episode is the third in our
year-long podcast series on global
credential solvency requirements which
will form the basis of our forthcoming
publication the Encyclopedia of
credential
solvency joining me today to unpack
Japanese presedential Insurance
regulation is my colleague Annabelle
smithurst it's great to have you here to
speak about this important topic I
should say that we're mostly grateful to
our good colleagues at scadden Tokyo for
their review of the script for this
podcast thanks Rob Japan is the fourth
largest Insurance Market in the world
holding a 5% global market share and
insurance premiums of 363 billion US in
2024 it follows only the US China and
the UK in its hold of the world's
Insurance Market traditionally dominated
by life insurance over recent Rec years
Japan's Insurance base has seen
increasing competition with the rise of
foreign insurers and New Market entrance
in the reinsurance
market the life insurance Market in
Japan is relatively
Consolidated there's only a total of 41
domestic entities on The Regulators list
of which 12 are foreign owned top
players amongst these domestic life
insurers have a significant role as
investors in Japanese and Global markets
with over2 trillion us do in
assets these domestic insurers have been
continually expanding overseas making
Acquisitions in the US and London
Insurance Market as well as investing in
Southeast Asia and the brick countries
Japan's declining population and the
resulting need for these life insurers
to diversify their traditional offering
has increase this acquisitive
Trend by comparison the fsa's list as of
the 23rd of December
2024 list 57 licensed non-life insurance
companies operating in Japan comprising
both domestic and foreign Branch
entities the Japanese Insurance Market
is attractive for foreign insurers for
several reasons for one it is one of the
largest and most mature Insurance
markets globally with a broad customer
base and a culture of high levels of
household savings providing opportun
unities for growth and investment
secondly Japan's aging population
creates demand for a range of offerings
particularly in the life and longer term
Health Care space providing a venue for
insurers to cater to evolving and unique
customer
needs lastly and importantly Japan's
Insurance Market is becoming
increasingly attractive to overseas
insurers due to ongoing regulatory
reforms aimed at improving Financial
stability and aligning Japan with
International standards in the past
Japan's Insurance sector was governed by
formal solvency
regulations these have in recent years
been revised by Japan's Financial
Services regulator the financial service
Services Agency or FSA which is an
external organ of the Japanese
government cabinet office the FSA has
aligned Japanese standards more closely
with global Frameworks such as solvency
and IIs and I
IC this shift is intended to enhance the
efficiency of the insurance Market by
introducing more sophisticated
risk-based requirements reflecting
insurers actual risk profiles instead of
relying solely on static Capital buffers
Japan began liberalizing its insurance
industry with the government's Financial
Big Bang in the
1990s where as part of an attempt to
remedy economic stagnation in the early
'90s the government introduced wide-
ranging plans to reregulate the
financial services Market modeled on a
similar framework globally insurance
regulations saw a shift from its
previous more rigid framework in favor
of Greater openness and
flexibility 1998 saw a relaxation of
fixed insurance rates for example
allowing insurers to compete more on
price and service the introduction of
the insurance business act in 1995
exemplified the spirit of liberalization
and led to the increased presence of
foreign life insurers sparking a period
of mass consolidation and restructuring
of the non-life market the ACT saw
industry Regulators take a more
principles L approach with a greater
emphasis on the protection of policy
holders the revised act also permitted
non-life insurers to enter into the
previously cordoned off life insurance
Market through subsidiary structures
promoting greater comp competition in
the area the insurance Act of Japan 2008
which came into force in 2010 modernized
insurance contract law in Japan both in
form and substance which had survived
for nearly a hundred years without
substantial
modification between 1997 in 2000 direct
foreign investment in Japan's Financial
Insurance sectors was 11 times what it
had been between 1989 and
1996 foreign insurers have since been
able to increase their market share
foreign insurers now account for eight
of the top 20 life insurers in Japan in
the non-life space 22 of 55 listed
general insurers in Japan are Branch
offices of Foreign Insurance companies
and seven of the remaining 33 domestic
insurers are deemed foreign owned
meaning they have an overseas held stake
of 50% or
more deregulation and the end of tariffs
in the late
1990s also ignited changes in
reinsurance purchasing in Japan despite
the size of the non-life market and
exposure to natural disasters a major
feature of the Japanese reinsurance
Market since the post-war period had
been for the bulk of reinsurance to be
retained with the market through a
variety of pooling arrangements and
exchanges for example the government
insured 60% of compulsory motor
insurance in the late 1990s with the
remaining 40% seeded to the compulsory
automobile liability insurance pool a
public private partnership involving
government
contributions it was only since the
liberalization of the '90s and a sweep
of natural disasters such as the typhoon
mual in
1991 with insured losses of $3.8
billion that these pooling structures
started disbanding and Japanese insurers
began to arrange their own reinsurance
facilities these movements in
reinsurance are only just about picking
up with further regulatory reforms on
the horizon stemming from this Japan is
becoming a real hub for reinsurance
activity Rob could you shed a little
color on the movement in that area
certainly Annabelle while Japanese
regulation allows for foreign insurers
to become licensed to operate in Japan
the practicalities of which we'll set
out later in this episode we've also
seen a flourishing of reinsurance
transactions in Japan structured through
reinsurance to Offshore
reinsurers Japan's primary insurance and
reinsurance sectors have experienced
Dynamic growth in recent years the
Japanese Market is both mature and
highly competitive both of which are
critical elements necessary for the
growth of
reinsurance as with the US recent
primary Insurance market growth in Japan
has been driven by sales of savings
oriented products for mortality and
annuity
segments these movements have been
driven by an aging population
also limitations on public health care
benefits mean that products offering
morbidity coverage are in high demand
the capital and asset intensive nature
of these products drives the need for
new Partnerships to assist primary
writers with sophisticated underwriting
for complex products balance sheet
relief for their Capital intensity and
related Asset Management
Partnerships reinsurance is an effective
tool to address all these obje
actives the last 18 or more months have
yielded a high volume of announced
transactions indicating the start of a
reinsurance boom these transactions are
structured both uh on an inforce or
block and flow basis and a designed to
achieve various objectives for the
Japanese students Annabelle could you
sketch out some general characteristics
of these transactions please of course
Rob most of these transactions are
characterized by a session from an
onshore Japanese life and annuity
insurer to an offshore reinsurer
generally a Bermuda classy long-term
insurer the fact that most of these
transactions involve a session to
Bermuda signals the fsa's comfort with
the
BMA which has also received equivalence
under EU and UK solvency to and with the
NAIC as a qualified jurisdiction
ition as a general Trend we've seen that
Partnerships are between the largest
players in the Japanese life annuity
market and usually large
reinsurers several enforced transactions
with seeded reserves in the
multi-billions may also signal a desire
for Capital
relief most significant transactions
have also been placed with reinsurers
affiliated with large asset managers
signaling that Japanese insurers are
looking for support with Investment
Management many such transactions have
been on a flow basis potentially
signaling a desire for support with
respect to asset origination at the time
of contract
Inception Rob now that we know a little
bit about this history and current
trends in the Japanese Insurance
landscape can you tell us about the
regulator and an overview of the
regulation in in Japan Prudential
regime yes with pleasure Japan's
insurance and reinsurance Industry is
regulated by the insurance business Act
of
1995 with supplemental rules in the
enforcement order of the insurance
business act 1995 and the ordinance for
the enforcement of the insurance
business act
1996 the regulatory Authority is the
Financial Services Agency or FSA which
is an integrated Financial regulator
reporting to the minister of State for
financial
services established by Statute the FSA
is responsible for ensuring the
stability of Japan's Financial system
and the protection of depositors
insurance policy holders and securities
investors a well functioning Financial
system for its planning and policymaking
activities and the inspection and
supervision of private sector financial
institutions and the surveillance of
Securities
transactions the FSA is empowered under
statute to lead planning and policym of
financial systems and plays a general
supervisory role in the writing of
insurance contracts and the activities
of insurance
companies based on the insurance
business act the FSA has the power to
issue administrative dispositions to
insurance companies including orders for
business Improvement orders for the
suspension of business and or orders for
the cancellation of
licenses in practice raw discretion is
given to the regulatory
authorities insurers not only have to
observe all laws and regulations but
must also follow the guidelines set by
the regulatory authorities the
comprehensive guidelines for the
supervision of
insurers thanks Rob how does solvency 2
relate to
Japan Japan has been deemed solvency 2
equivalent and was one of the first
countries covered by the first wave of
the equivalence assessment it was
granted temporary equivalence for
reinsurance which expired as of the 31st
December
2020 a joint statement by the FSA the
European commission and eopa was issued
on 21st December 2020 to address the
expiry of this temporary equivalence and
the future implementation of Japan's
economic value-based solvency
regime in addition Japan has been
granted provisional equivalence for
group solvency until 1st January
2026 in practice this means that UK and
EU Insurance Groups can conduct their
credential reporting for a subsidiary in
Japan under local rules instead of
solvency 2 provided that they are
authorized to use deduction and
aggregation as their method of
consolidating group accounts alongside
reinsurance
equivalents as we'll go on to discuss
later in the episode The FSA has also
since established an advisory Council on
economic value based solvency and is
looking to implement an economic
value-based solvency regulatory
framework over the next year that is set
to be closely aligned with solvency 2
and the
IC Anabel now that we know about Japan's
regulator and regulation can you provide
some more detail as to the requirements
of the Japan credential regime
especially with foreign insurer
participation in mind certainly Rob
firstly insurance companies are strictly
defined under statute and as is the case
in many regimes are not permitted to
conduct any business other than
underwriting insurance and any
incidental business to the core
Insurance business incidental business
is limited to the description in the IBA
and not widely
interpreted insurance companies are also
restricted with respect to ownership of
subsidiaries in accordance with the IBA
which includes restricting the ownership
of non-insurance
businesses insurers are not allowed to
own subsidiaries that perform businesses
other than Insurance business or
business incidental to Insurance nor are
they allowed to obtain stake in domestic
non-insurance companies in excess of 10%
of those companies total voting rights
however with the approval of the
regulatory authorities Insurance holding
companies may have non-insurance
companies as their subsidiaries that
insurers themselves may not own and are
not subject to these stringent
restrictions but subject to slightly
relaxed restrictions on the scope of
business life insurance and non-life
insurance remain strictly divided in
Japan with different types of licenses
required for
each licenses for life insurance and
non-life insurance business cannot be
acquired by the same company so
companies are prohibited from running
both businesses concurrently Composites
are not
permitted however both life insurers and
non-life insurers are free to offer
Insurance in the So-Cal third sector
Insurance market for example medical
care insurance accident insurance or
overseas travel
insurance statute also imposes a minimum
Capital requirement on insurance
companies a minimum of 1 billion
Japanese Yen which is approximately 6.7
million us
do the same general restrictions apply
to foreign insurers foreign insurers are
only allowed to conduct Insurance
business in Japan if they have opened
either a local Japanese subsidiary in
the form of a Japanese stock company
under the company acts of Japan or a
branch in Japan where instead of capital
requirements the branch is required to
deposit a minimum of 200 million
Japanese Yen which is approximately $1.3
million us to the deposit off office to
protect policy
holders once they have opened a
subsidiary or branch in Japan foreign
insurers then have to obtain an
applicable license from the FSA this
requirement allows the FSA to have
administrative power over such foreign
insurers the general rule is that unless
they are licensed foreign insurers um
are prohibited from concluding any
insurance contracts that insure any
person person with an address residence
or property in Japan or a vessel or
aircraft registered in the country Rob
could you shed a little light on
applying for a license sure Annabelle as
discussed earlier a license is not
issued unless the FSA is convinced of
The credibility of the applicant in
terms of sufficient Financial assets
human resources and business
projections during the licensing
procedure the FSA examines the company's
documents including General policy
conditions the business method statement
the premium and Reserve calculation
method statement business projections
generally for 10 years directors resumés
and information on major shareholders of
the
applicant in terms of timings the FSA
Endeavors to make decisions whether to
Grant a license within 120 days after
receipt of the licensing
application this is called the the
standard processing period however this
rule only applies on a best Endeavors
basis and is interpreted to commence
when the formal application documents
are filed in practice the foreign
insurer or its subsidiary will hold many
discussions with the FSA about the
application documents before the formal
filing and this discussion period will
likely take at least a year note that
strict penalties apply engaging in
Insurance Business Without necessary
license is subject to punishment by
maximum 3 years imprisonment or a
maximum 3 million yen fine are there
exceptions yes there are exceptions
certain limited exceptions do exist for
certain insurance contracts foreign
insurers may enter into insurance
contracts without obtaining the
applicable
license reinsurance contracts are
included in this
exemption the licensing restriction does
not apply to any insurance contract
where the FSA has granted Advanced
permission to an applicant wishing to
purchase insurance from an unlicensed
Foreign Insurance
Company let's look a little deeper into
the first of the exceptions which
relates to reinsurance transactions by
Foreign
companies by analogy the appropriate
test looks similar to the characteristic
performance test familiar in the UK and
Europe in order to determine the
regulatory
perimeter under the Japanese regime if a
reinsurer operates business on an
offshore basis that is conducting all
underwriting claims handling contract
negotiations and other activities from
outside Japan and not utilizing its own
employees or agents to conduct any such
activities in Japan then it is not
required to be licensed and therefore
will not be subject to FSA
supervision any regulatory including
reporting obligations or any Capital
requirements regardless of the amount of
business it conducts with Japanese
cedant Japanese cedant in turn are
subject to regulatory requirements to
obtain credit for reinsurance on their
financial statements and may request
such information from foreign reinsurers
in order to comply with their regulatory
obligations reinsurance transactions
between Japanese insurers as well as
those with overseas insurers that are
licensed in Japan a class as generally
exempt from the general requirement on
licensed insurers to hold policy
reserves for the policies they have
insured Japanese cedant will get credit
for reinsurance in respect to policy
reserving however there must be a high
possibility of recovery under the
reinsurance
contracts they also must do their due
diligence to understand the reinsurance
counterparty in as much detail as
possible in order to evaluate the
possibility of such
recovery this exemption may also be
invoked by Japanese cedant in respect of
foreign reinsurers but only to the
extent that the reinsurance would not
impair the financial soundness of the
cedant considering the foreign reinsurer
business and financial
condition there is no specific test
based on specific monetary thresholds or
limits regarding this
exemption however the FSA guidelines
suggest that this exemption may be
invoked in respect of foreign reinsurers
for example where the maximum
reinsurance payment per single insured
event is less than 1% of the sedent
total assets or in cases where the
cedant has not accumulated liability
reserves corresponding to the part for
which the reinsurance is affected and
the foreign reinsurer assumed the
reinsurance in each case there must be
no concern that the foreign reinsurer
would fail to make the reinsurance
payments due to insolvency or other
reasons in practice this means that
Japanese students may ask a foreign
reinsurer for information materials and
other evidence regarding the foreign
reinsurers business and financial
condition in order to Avail of this
exemption to hold policy
reserves we should note that in late
January 2025 it was reported that the
FSA has started to survey Japanese life
insurers to examine potential risks tied
to their rapidly grow growing practice
of transferring policy liabilities to
reinsurers often backed by global
private Equity firms according to a
March 2025 report the FSA is reportedly
asking Japanese life insurers about the
scale of their reinsurance practices and
the types of contracts they have in
place and are also interested in the
concentration of risks with reinsurers
operating in
Bermuda note that despite this attention
there had been no official announcement
or regulatory actions by the FSA so far
only reports that this information
gathering exercise is taking place this
may suggest however that the FSA would
consider introducing new regulations or
restrictions on reinsurance transactions
in the near
future Annabelle we've talked a bit
about licensing requirements and capital
requirements are there also fronting
restrictions under the Japanese rules
thanks Rob no fronting is not expressed
prohibited or permitted in Japan and
there are no explicit expectations with
regards to the cedant
retention Rob we hinted earlier that the
Japanese Prudential landscape is
evolving could you provide a little more
color on this yes Annabelle of prime
importance the new economic value-based
solvency regulations that Japan is
looking to
introduce the FSA is preparing to align
these with the insurance Capital
standard or IC
issued by the International Association
of Insurance supervisors or
IIs in final form in December 2024 as
discussed in our January
podcast due to the introduction of the
these new regulations many Japanese
insurance companies especially life
insurance companies are considering
entering into new reinsurance agreements
with
reinsurers sometimes in respect of quota
share reinsurance of future premiums
called flow re insurance and reinsurance
of blocks of existing business called
block reinsurance often in the form of
asset intensive reinsurance or funded
reinsurance which is gaining momentum in
the Japanese life insurance Market this
is because the type of liability is
found in Japan can be profoundly
affected by fluctuations in interest
rates especially when an insurer has
existing blocks of insurance contracts
with high long-term interest rates
meaning reinsurance agreements are seen
as a way to hedge against this
risk with this in mind we are seeing a
real blossoming of reinsurance deals in
the Japanese Market which is ripe for
overseas
participation in terms of timing for
these new economic solvency regulations
the FSA is planning to implement them
from the fiscal year ending march
2026 insurance companies in Japan are
expected to submit business reports
pursuant to the new legislation from the
fiscal year year ending march
2026 Rob do these new solvency
regulations seem likely to depart in any
way from the ICS or will they be fully
aligned yes more or less Japan's new
regulations are designed to be generally
aligned with IC but with slight
adjustments tailored to Japanese
insurance companies for example the
coefficient for calculating life
insurance and non-life insurance risks
will be calibrated to reflect the
characteristics of Japanese insurance
companies many of Japan's insurers are
small or mediumsized whereas the
coefficient in the calculation of IC is
based on data mainly collected from
large International Insurance
Groups now that we've talked about some
considerations regarding the new
regulations why don't we go over a few
more links between Japan and the UK
Insurance World thanks Rob Japanese
insurers do interact with the UK
regulatory regime in number of notable
areas historically Japanese insurers
have used the part 7 process in the UK
to transfer their insurance Li
liabilities which is affected by the
courts in the UK to another insurer
including where both the transfer raw
and the transfery insurers are Japanese
insurers in circumstances where part
seven can apply while a statutory
transfer mechanism for books of
insurance does exist in Japan this
requires the authorization of the Prime
Minister a special resolution of the
shareholders of both the transferor and
the transferee and the notified consent
of all affected policy
holders however several Japanese
insurers have historically opted to use
the part 7even process in the UK to
dispose of Legacy businesses and action
portfolio
transfers moreover several of the
leading Japanese trading companies have
historically set up Insurance broking
subsidiaries in the UK in order to
become involved in the insurance
Arrangements of their parent companies
in the absence of an equivalent
framework being available under Japanese
law we have also seen Japanese insurance
companies making sustained outbound deal
activity as they pursue business outside
their home Market the main driver for
this m&a is promoting diversification
where a shrinking population has weighed
on domestic growth at the same time as
we have discussed Foreign Insurance
companies and insurance brokers are
increasingly making inroads into the
Japanese
markets thank you Annabelle that brings
us to the end of today's episode it's
evident that the regulatory framework in
Japan is designed to balance the
protection of policy holders and
Regulatory equivalence with the need for
insurers and Japan to remain competitive
not only are Japanese insurance
companies vibrant participants in the
global market we're increasingly seeing
overseas insurers and reinsurers make
the most of insurance opportunities
ripening in
Japan in summary we expect that the
strength of the Japanese insurance
industry and the fsa's encouragement of
innovation will lead to further
regulatory Evolution as new challenges
arise Japan is rapidly adapting its
regime to be equivalent with
International credential mechanisms in
order to preserve its position within
the global insurance Market both on the
seant side and reinsurance side as
exemplified in the New Economic solvency
regulations and the welcoming of
overseas participation in the Japanese
reinsurance
space we look forward to welcoming you
to the next episode of our podcast which
will cover the Cayman Islands thank you
for listening
today thank you for joining us on the
standard formula if you enjoyed this
conversation be sure to subscribe in
your favorite podcast app so you don't
miss any future episodes additional
information about scadden can be found
at
scad.edu
and reinsurance companies and their
advisers on a wide variety of
transactional and Regulatory matters
this podcast is provided for educational
and informational purposes only and is
not intended and should not be construed
as legal advice this podcast is
considered advertising under applicable
state laws